Hi, this is Matt Baker. Earlier this
year, we launched our timeline of space
exploration chart, at which point we
also did an episode on missions to the
moon in order to help celebrate Aremis
2. Well, today we're going to continue
the series. This time focusing on the
first space stations as well as the
space shuttles. But before we begin, if
you want to get a copy of the chart as a
poster, it's available as a
highresolution print on thick quality
paper over on our website,
usefulcharts.com.
The chart covers every major space
mission from 1957 all the way to the
missions planned for the 2030s. It
includes both human missions as well as
robotic missions, which have reached as
far as Pluto and beyond. We also have a
timeline of world history and a tree of
life poster as well as lots of family
trees covering Roman emperors, European
monarchs, and Asian monarchs. Again, if
you're interested in learning more about
any of these wall charts, just head over
to usefulcharts.com
or simply click the link in the
description or pinned comment. Okay.
Now, one of the reasons why I covered
lunar missions first is because that's
what the earliest human space programs
were all about. It was a race between
the United States and the Soviet Union
to see who could put a man on the moon
first. It was only after the US achieved
that goal that both countries focused on
low Earth orbit instead. As I mentioned
last time, compared to the moon, low
Earth orbit is much closer to home.
Basically, it's anything between 160 km
above the surface to 2,000 km above the
surface. Now, don't get me wrong,
launching humans that high is still a
big deal. To put it in perspective,
commercial airlines fly at around 10 km
above the surface, whereas the
International Space Station flies at 400
km above the surface. So, that's 40
times higher. And of course, when you
ride on an airplane, you don't
experience weightlessness. whereas in
low earth orbit you do. Now returning to
the timeline by 1970 there were two main
spacecraft designs in existence. The
Soviets had the Soyuse 7K whereas the
Americans had the Apollo command module.
However, neither spacecraft was reusable
which meant that for every mission a new
copy had to be built. By this point the
Soviets had given up on going to the
moon. So instead they focused on
building the world's first ever space
station, the Salute 1. In April of 1971,
they launched the station, unoccupied of
course, as well as a separate Soyuse
spacecraft with three cosmonauts whose
mission was to dock with and board the
Salute 1. They however failed due to a
computer malfunction and had to return
to Earth. But about 6 weeks later, the
Suyuse 11 mission was launched again
with three astronauts. This time they
were able to board Solude 1, where they
stayed for 24 days, which at the time
was the longest anyone had ever spent in
space. However, on the way back to
Earth, tragedy struck. Just before
re-entering the Earth's atmosphere, a
valve broke, depressurizing the cabin.
The [clears throat] spacecraft landed on
autopilot with no other damage. But when
the ground crew opened the capsule, they
found all three cosminauts dead.
Presumably, they died as soon as that
valve leaked, making them the only space
travelers to ever actually die in space.
This is because all other space related
deaths have occurred within the Earth's
atmosphere during either takeoff or
landing. Because of the Soyos 11
tragedy, the Soviets redesigned the
Soyos. Meaning that for the next little
bit, we'll be dealing with the second
generation of the spacecraft known as
the 7KT. T standing for transport
because its main goal was to safely
transport cosminauts to and from space
stations. The Soviet's second space
station was Salute 2, launched in 1973.
However, after 2 weeks, it malfunctioned
and therefore was never visited. Now,
take note that I've also labeled it as
Almos 1. That's because it was actually
a secret military space station. The
West only learned its true name, Almas,
after the collapse of the Soviet Union.
Almas 2, known at the time as Salute 3,
was launched the following year. And
this time, everything worked and it was
able to be visited by Suyuse 14.
However, most importantly, Almos 2 is
unique in that it is the only spacecraft
in history to ever fire a weapon. Now,
take note that this actually happened
when no cosminauts were on board with
the ground crew controlling the gun
remotely because they weren't exactly
sure what would happen. Okay. The next
Soviet space station was Solute 4, which
was a civilian station. It was visited
twice, starting with Soyuse 17. Take
note that not all missions are shown on
this chart, just some of the more
notable ones. Next came Solute 5, which
was really Almas 3. It too was visited
twice, starting with Soyuse 21, but this
time no guns were fired. But then came
Salute 6, which was a gamecher. You see,
up to this point, no space station had
been designed to be used long-term. So,
in many ways, Salute 6 was the first
real space station, meaning that it was
designed to stay in space for many years
and to be visited many times. But before
I tell you about it, I want to go back
and tell you what the United States was
up to during the 1970s. The last Apollo
mission to the moon was Apollo 17 in
December of 1972. Take note that
originally there was supposed to be
three additional lunar missions, Apollo,
18, 19, and 20, but those were cancelled
so that the US could instead focus on
the space shuttle program, which we'll
get to in a bit. But first, I want to
point out the Apollo applications
program, which you may not know about.
You see, the US had a perfectly good
spacecraft, the Apollo command module.
So even though it was no longer going to
go to the moon, they could do other
stuff with it instead. So the first
thing it was used for was the Skyab
missions. Skyab being the first and
today only American space station. It
was visited three times using Apollo
spacecraft with the missions officially
being called Skyab 2, 3, and 4, although
they are also known as Skyab 1, 2, and 3
because NASA made a mistake with the
first badge. and then they just went
with it. The other thing the Apollo
spacecraft was used for was the Apollo
Syuse mission, the first ever joint
mission between two countries in space.
On July 15th, 1975, the Soviets launched
a specially modified Soyuse spacecraft
and the Americans launched a specially
modified Apollo spacecraft. Two days
later, they met in space and docked with
each other so that the Russian
cosminauts and American astronauts could
shake hands and visit each other's
spacecrafts. The mission ended up being
a symbol of how cold war tensions eased
during the 70s before ramping up again
during the 80s. Let's now return to
Salute 6, the first real space station.
It was visited by six long-term crews
with the longest day being 85 days,
which was more than double the longest
Skylab stay. But the other
groundbreaking thing about Salute 6 was
that it was also visited by 10
short-term crews, most of which included
for the first time ever astronauts from
countries other than the US and the
Soviet Union. So we got the first
Czechlovakian in space, the first Pole,
the first East German, Bulgarian,
Hungarian, Vietnamese person who was
also the first Asian in space, the first
Cuban, and the first Mongolian. Now,
what do you notice about all of these
countries? Well, at the time, they were
all communist and closely aligned with
the Soviets. But then came the salute 7
space station which was paired with the
third generation Soyuse spacecraft
simply called the Soyuse T. This time
non-communist countries were invited to
send astronauts. So we got the first
Western European in space a Frenchman as
well as the first Indian. There likely
would have been more foreign nationals
sent, but in 1985, Soviet mission
control lost contact with Salute 7,
which at the time was unoccupied.
Basically, the station lost power and
went dead. But instead of giving up on
it, the Soviets sent a crew aboard
Soyuse T13 to see if they could do
repairs. When they arrived, they found
the station ice cold inside. But over
the next few days, they were able to fix
things and get the station up and
running again. For the Soviets, this was
their equivalent of the US's Apollo 13
moment. And as such, the whole thing has
been made into a movie called Salute 7.
Unfortunately, however, it does not star
Tom Hanks. Now the Soviets continued to
use Salute 7 into the following year
1986 but at the same time they started
building a new space station called Mir.
Thus for a brief period there were two
operational space stations in orbit for
the first time ever. In fact the Suyu's
T15 mission visited both of them. First
docking with Mir becoming its first crew
and then second docking with the Salute
7 becoming the last crew of the Salute
program. Now take note that Mir was
different from all previous space
stations in that it was the first
modular space station. This means that
it grew in size over time as more parts
were added to it. So in the beginning it
looked like this but by the end it
looked like this. Also take note that
after Soyuse T-15, all of the remaining
Soviet missions to MIR used the fourth
generation Soyuse spacecraft known as
the Soyuse TM. The M standing for
modified. So, as you've probably noticed
by now, unlike in the US, where NASA has
designed several very different crude
spacecrafts, the Soviets, soon to become
the Russians, basically just kept the
same basic design, upgrading and
improving it about once per decade.
Another important first for Mir was that
it became the first space station to be
continuously occupied. Not initially,
but from 1989 onwards. So instead of
sending crews, bringing them home and
then sending the next crew, they started
to overlap the crews so that there was
always someone on board. And once again,
some of the crews included foreign
nationals, including the first
astronauts from Syria, Afghanistan,
Japan, the United Kingdom, and Austria.
Toyohiro Akiyama's trip was notable in
that it was the first to be paid for by
a commercial company. In this case, the
Tokyo Broadcasting System. You see,
Akiyama was a journalist. So, he ended
up becoming the first journalist to
report from space. Helen Charman's trip
was also funded privately, this time by
a bunch of companies who ran a lottery
to see who would become the first
British person in space. Now, just after
Charman's mission came Soyuse TM13,
which ended up being unique in that it
took off from the Soviet Union, but
landed in a newly independent
Kazakhstan. This is because during the
flight, the Soviet Union fell, being
replaced by several independent states,
the main one, of course, being Russia.
So, take note that from here on out,
we'll be dealing with Russian missions,
not Soviet ones. Even though the
Russians still launch from the Biconor
Cosmo Drrome located in Kazakhstan,
basically the Russians now have to pay
Kazakhstan rent to use the spaceport.
Now, while I'm here, I want to point out
Valeri Paleakov. Initially a Soviet
astronaut, but later a Russian one. He
is important because in 1995 he set the
record for the longest single stay in
space when he spent 438 straight days
aboard Mir. That record still stands but
take note that when it comes to the most
cumulative days in space the record
holder is Russian cosminaut Oleg Kanenko
who across five missions has spent a
total of 1,111
days which is just over 3 years. All
right, at this point I once again want
to back up and talk about the United
States, namely their space shuttle
program, which had its first launch in
1981. Take note that STS stands for
space transport system, which was the
official name for the space shuttles.
Now, the reason why the space shuttles
were so special was that they were
reusable. Initially, NASA built four of
them named Colombia, Challenger,
Discovery, and Atlantis. The idea was
that instead of building another US
space station, they could instead send
up space shuttles on a regular basis and
use their large cargo bays to do the
same kind of stuff that the Soviets were
doing in Salute 7 and Mir. The first
space shuttle flight STS1 was commended
by John Young, who I want to take a
moment to highlight because in my
opinion, he deserves to be the most
famous astronaut of all time, even more
famous than Neil Armstrong. Even though
in reality, very few people actually
know his name. Let me give you a quick
rundown of his resume. He's the only
person to have both walked on the moon
and flown on a space shuttle. He's the
only person to fly aboard four different
spacecraft, the Gemini, the Apollo
Command module, the Apollo lunar module,
and the Space Shuttle. He's one of only
three people to have flown to the moon
twice, even though he landed on the moon
only once. He was the first astronaut to
fly to space six times. And he was the
longest serving astronaut of all time,
serving for 42 years. So John Young,
folks, remember his name. Now, another
important thing about the space shuttle
program is that it was very
collaborative with lots of other
countries involved. For example, my own
country, Canada, built the Canada arm,
which was a robotic arm installed for
the first time on STS3 and used for
things like launching satellites and
supporting spacew walks. There was also
space lab built by the European Space
Agency. It was placed in the cargo hold
during certain missions and used as a
laboratory for experiments. It flew for
the first time during STS9 along with
West Germany's first astronaut. Other
missions during these early years of the
space shuttle program included the first
US woman in space, Sally Ride, as well
as the first black American, the first
Canadian, Dutchman, [clears throat]
Mexican, and Saudi Arabian, who was also
the first and today only royal to go to
space. Also of note is the STS41B
mission during which Bruce McCandless
performed the first ever untethered
spacew walk which was captured in this
now famous photo. But then of course
came the event that is perhaps the most
remembered thing about the space shuttle
program, the Challenger disaster, which
involved an explosion during takeoff
that killed all seven astronauts on
board, including a civilian named
Christa McAuliffe, who was going to be
the first teacher in space. It is
estimated that 2 and a half million
school children were watching live when
it happened, and thus it became
generation X's. where were you when
moment. Now, I should probably explain
why that fateful mission was called
STS51L
because it wasn't the 51st space shuttle
flight. It was actually the 25th.
Ironically, in order to avoid having an
unlucky STS13 mission, NASA adopted a
somewhat complicated numbering system
for a while. So the five actually stood
for the fact that the mission was
originally planned for 1985.
The one stood for the fact that it took
off from Kennedy Space Center and the L
stood for the fact that it was supposed
to be the 12th flight of the year.
Thankfully NASA reverted back to the
simpler numbering system after the
disaster, but they did wait more than a
year and a half with the next mission
being SDS26 in 1988. As you can see,
this was followed up by several
important deployments. For example,
instead of launching from the ground,
the Mellan Venus probe and the Galileo
Jupiter probe were deployed from the
space shuttle. Then, of course, there
was the famous Hubble Space Telescope
deployed from a shuttle in 1990. It gave
us some amazing pictures of the
universe. Following the Challenger
disaster, NASA also built a replacement
shuttle called Endeavor. It flew for the
first time in 1992.
Now, as we've already seen, by this
point, the Soviet Union had fell. And
this was very important for space
exploration because it opened up doors
for the two main space fairing
countries, the US and Russia, to start
working together on a more regular
basis. So, in 1994, we got the first
Russian to fly aboard a US space
shuttle. And in 1995, we got the first
American to fly aboard a soyuse and
visit Mir. That same year, during SDS63,
we also got the near Mir mission in
which the space shuttle came in close
contact with the Mir station for the
first time ever, although it didn't
actually dock. That happened a few
months later during SDS71,
which was the first of nine times that
the shuttle docked with Mir. However, by
this point, plans were already underway
to build a new space station, the
International Space Station or ISS,
which would be operated by both Russia
and the US, as well as a bunch of other
partners, namely Canada, Japan, and the
European Union. What happened was this.
Originally, the US had been planning to
build something called Space Station
Freedom, and Russia was planning to
build Mir 2. But in the end, the
individual plans were scrapped and
instead combined to create the
International Space Station. The
station's first component, the Russian
Zarya module, was launched on its own in
November of 1998. Then in December, the
US Unity node was brought up by STS88
and connected to Zarya using the Cannid
Arm. Thus began the International Space
Station. Further construction took place
throughout 1999 with the SDS96 crew
being the first to dock with and enter
the station. They, however, are not
considered expedition one. Expeditions
being the long-term crews that have been
continuously rotating for over 25 years
now. The expedition 1 crew arrived
aboard soyuse TM31
6 months after soy TM30 which was the
last mission to visit Mir. Other early
components of the ISS included the
Zvezda and Destiny modules as well as
the Canadarmm 2. So by expedition 2, the
ISS looked something like this.
Sveveszda, the main Russian module,
controlled navigation and was used as
sleeping quarters. Whereas Destiny, the
main US module, served as a science lab.
Zarya was mostly used for storage and
Unity, well, it basically held the two
sides together, hence the name. Now,
during Expedition 2, another key event
occurred. The arrival of the first space
tourist, Dennis Tito, a billionaire who
paid $20 million to visit the station
for 8 days. Since this groundbreaking
trip, an additional 12 space tourists
have also visited the ISS, with the
price tag currently being around $70
million per person. Okay, that brings us
to the end of episode two. In episode 3,
I'll cover the continuing evolution of
the International Space Station, what
the space shuttle was eventually
replaced with, and finally, the arrival
on the scene of a third major space
fairing country, China. Until then, be
sure to check out the link in the pinned
comment, so that you can get your own
copy of our timeline of space
exploration. Thanks for watching.